Normand Louis LaRoche papers, Inclusive: 1917-1948, undated, Bulk: 1944-1945
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Normand Louis LaRoche papers
Inclusive: 1917-1948, undated, Bulk: 1944-1945
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
643
LaRoche, Normand Louis, 1916 - 1977
3 document boxes and 4 oversize boxes
The Normand Louis LaRoche papers contain a variety of documents and materials related to LaRoche’s experiences serving in the United States Army during World War II, including his time overseeing prisoners of war in Camp Milam, Texas, and serving in the military police in Europe.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Normand Lois LaRoche was born 1916 September 6. In 1943, having enlisted in the United States Army, Corporal LaRoche was transferred to Camp Huntsville, Texas. By 1944 January, he was promoted to the rank of sergeant. Later that year, he transferred to Camp Milam, where he oversaw prisoner of war work details.
In 1945, LaRoche served in the military police in Europe. He was first posted in Brussels, Belgium, during the final months of World War II. After the war, he remained in Europe, serving in post-war Berlin from 1945 October to 1946 February. During the final days of 1945, he went on furlough, traveling throughout Switzerland. He died on 1977 October 18.
Scope and Content
The Normand Louis LaRoche papers consist of materials from 1917-1948, with some undated items. The papers reflect LaRoche’s experience serving in the Army during World War II, especially his time overseeing prisoner of war work details at Camp Milam and his experiences in Belgium, Switzerland, and Germany during the conclusion and aftermath of World War II. The majority of the materials are in English, though some items are in French and German.
Series I, Prisoner of War Camp Documents, contains memos, prisoner counts, transfer lists, and other documents related to overseeing work details at Camp Milam. The finding aid for this series retains an acronym (T.T.S.P.) in the folder titles because no information could be found regarding the acronym's meaning. Series II, Literary productions, contains books and booklets related to LaRoche’s time in the military. Series III, Personal Materials, contains a wide variety of materials connected to LaRoche’s experiences in the military, including physical objects, notebooks, correspondence, photographs, postcards, currency, and other assorted items. Of particular note are three scrapbooks recording LaRoche’s time in Brussels, Switzerland, and Berlin.
Arrangement
The Normand Louis LaRoche papers arrived in an old suitcase. Three folders of documents, several objects (mostly cloth items), and an assortment of books, booklets, and envelopes were stuffed into the left side of the suitcase. Three scrapbooks were placed in the right side of the suitcase. Most of the materials appeared to be in no clear order. However, the documents bound in the folders were consistently organized chronologically. Some of the documents placed loose in the folders were also organized chronologically.
The collection is currently divided into three series: I. Prisoner of War Camp Documents, II. Literary Productions, and III: Personal Materials. The documents in folders were combined into Series I, retaining their folder titles. Loose documents in the folders were arranged by type and then chronologically. Bound documents in the folder retain their original order. The published books and booklets comprise Series II and were organized by type. The remainder of the materials form Series III and were organized by type. The notebooks were arranged chronologically. The contents of the envelopes, the wallet, and the scrapbooks retain their original order. Several maps housed in the scrapbooks were moved into [1029] OVZ.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 643. Acquired 2020-08-26
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. “Normand L. LaRoche.” Memorial #131358496. Databases. Accessed 2020 October 1.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. Army.
Subjects
Military police -- Europe.; Prisoners of war -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Books.; Memorandums.; Realia.; Registers (Lists).; Reports.; Scrapbooks.
- Prisoner of War Camp Documents, 1944, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  Series I, Prisoner of War Camp Documents, contains memos, prisoner counts, transfer lists, and other documents related to overseeing work details at Camp Milam. The series is in poor condition.
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Army Talk, 1944 October 7-14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Pass List and Confiscated Items, 1944 October 21-December 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Work Details, 1944 October 21-December 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Assorted Documents, 1944 October 23-December 13, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: POW Memo no. 17, 1944 November 6-15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Transfers to Fort Bliss, 1944 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Transfers to Fort Crockett, 1944 December 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Transfers to Huntsville, 1944 December 16, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Loose Materials: Transfers to Claiborne and Camp Fannin, 1944 December 16-17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Details Daily Production Reports: Bound Materials, 1944 November 9-December 11, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Prisoner of War Monthly Report: Loose Materials: Labor Report Instructions and Laundry Receipt, 1944 June 1-October 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Prisoner of War Monthly Report: Loose Materials: Daily Labor Reports, 1944 October 16-December 20, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Prisoner of War Monthly Report: Loose Materials: Labor Spreadsheets, 1944 October 16-December 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Prisoner of War Monthly Report: Loose Materials: Transfer Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Prisoner of War Monthly Report: Bound Materials, 1944 September 15-November 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Prisoner of War Counts (Morn.) (Even.): Woodcutting Details, 1944 August 1-November 18, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Prisoner of War Counts (Morn.) (Even.): Memos, 1944 August 10-November 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Prisoner of War Counts (Morn.) (Even.): Prisoner Work Details, 1944 September 1-December 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Prisoner of War Counts (Morn.) (Even.): Employment Rosters and Compound Overhead, 1944 September 21-October 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Prisoner of War Counts (Morn.) (Even.): Incident Reports, 1944 November 7, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Medical Notes, 1944 September 15-November 13, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Prisoner Counts, 1944 September 15-30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Prisoner Counts, 1944 October 1-31 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Prisoner Counts, 1944 November 1-30 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Prisoner Counts, 1944 December 1-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Transfers to Camp Fannin, 1944 September 16-October 31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Transfers to Camp Fannin, 1944 November 1-December 13 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Transfers to Camp San Augustine, 1944 September 21-December 11 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Transfers to Camp Milam, 1944 September 22-December 14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - T.T.S.P. Details Check: Transfers to Other Camps, 1944 September 27-December 13 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Literary Productions, 1917-1944, undated; 2
  General condition: Average.
  Series II, Literary productions, contains books and booklets related to LaRoche’s time in the military.
  - Catholic Booklets, 1917-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Murder Recalls Van Kill, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Basic Field Manuals, 1941 August 4-1943 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Red Cross First Aid Texts, 1933-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rifle Score Books, 1942 March 29 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scouting and Patrolling, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Military Booklets, 1944, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Personal Materials, 1923-1946, undated; 3
  Series III, Personal Materials, contains a wide variety of materials connected to LaRoche’s experiences in the military, including physical objects, notebooks, correspondence, photographs, postcards, currency, and other assorted items. Of particular note are three scrapbooks recording LaRoche’s time in Brussels, Switzerland, and Berlin.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print; Postcards
  - Notebooks: Prisoner of War Camp, 1943 June14-1944 August 19 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notebooks: Europe, 1945 June 23-October4 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notebooks: Switzerland Furlough Diary, 1945 December 21-1948 September 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - War Department Envelope, 1943 August 17-1944 November 7, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Envelope 17229964, 1923 October 15-1946 February 19, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Wallet Contents, 1939 June -1944 December 25, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - MP Armbands, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Medal and St. Moritz Photocards, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Brussels Scrapbook, 1942 March 26-1945 July 29, undated (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Brussels Scrapbook, undated (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Switzerland Scrapbook, 1945 December 10-1946 January 4, undated (Box 5 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Switzerland Scrapbook, 1945 December 26, undated (Box [1029] OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Berlin Scrapbook Loose Materials, 1945 October 8-1946 February 18 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Berlin Scrapbook, 1944 October 7-1945 November 22, undated (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Berlin Scrapbook, 1944 (Box [1029], Folder 3)